here so welcome to today's solution
raising i'm excited because today we're
solution raising solution raising
so i invited people who have been
several times to solution raisings to
discuss
we're going to do it exactly the same i
was going to break the last part but i
actually like it that way
so what we what it's been like for us so
far what we would love it to look like
and then what we could do with ten
thousand people and a hundred thousand
dollars i was gonna
lower the amount but with this uh mlm
i'm creating and having the first
meeting with tomorrow i think we can
easily get to ten thousand i'm more
looking for a process
the ten thousand people can do so i'm
keeping it at that same
those same numbers um but if we come up
with something that a hundred people or
a thousand people do that would be great
too
um so i can definitely start this part
but anyone else can start as well
what has solution raisings looked like
for you so far what have you liked what
haven't you liked
uh i i like the conversations i like the
conversations and i like seeing what
people got to say
and i like the the meeting obviously i
haven't been because i've been depressed
and
feeling like so um
yeah i i i like him because it makes you
think about certain things and
that's what i like and i think jubilee
you're a really good host
as well so um yeah and i like meeting
people as well
so so yeah so i like that so i think
it's a good chance to me
and whether you know anything about what
topic is being discovered
you know i mean or talked about um
stuff like that so that's what i like
anything
what could improve or anything that's uh
that that
other half of it uh
anthony
i think i think what i don't like is
when people turn up and go what are we
talking about today
what are we what are we what are we
talking about
no that's just that just makes me
chuckle really because i'm thinking all
right okay
the world's about to go to and it's
okay to smile
and but yeah that's um there's not
really much that i don't like about it
really
because as i said it gets you to give
you the chance of what other people
think
and stuff like that and also to get to
see their thoughts and opinions
as well so that's and as i said most of
the time it's stuff that you may not
have thought of yourself
so i think that's that's there's not
much i dislike about it really
yeah i mean i think i think a very um
[Music]
inspiring thing it does is that it shows
that a handful of people because there's
not men
not usually more than three or four of
us at these things right
um and very often pretty much the same
three or four
and and but even given that
it's amazing how often we do come up
with something that if we did have you
know
the manpower and the resources it would
seemingly at least i mean you don't know
until you try right but seeming at least
like
be really quite effective and so you
know if
that could be scaled up to having dozens
hundreds of
brains involved then potentially so long
as you can figure out a way and i know
this is exactly what you're doing right
as long as you can figure out a way of
actually making that
work right creating a synergistic
framework within
which that can happen rather than you
know
all just sort of boils away kind of
thing
um which is no easy task right but but
if you can do that the potential
for coming up with and
acting out solutions to big problems on
a small scale which can then grow into
solutions on a big scale right um yeah
no i mean i think i think
i think it has real potential so yeah i
mean what you need to do is exactly what
you've just said and what you are doing
is figure out a way
to get more people involved in doing
this kind of thing and and turn the
the conversation the blah blah blah into
actual action in the real world i mean
that's that's the next step isn't it and
we've done enough of these things now
that
i think you know anyone who's been
involved in them can be convinced that
there is definitely potential for
creative problem solving um so
yeah it's it's now now a question of
expanding it so yeah good luck
good luck i hope the mlm thing works as
a as a as an attractor you know what i
mean to
to get the whole ball rolling
right thank you um if nothing else this
this hour
this one makes me feel good that i
created it so that's we'll see
what happens later but my experience so
far in solution raising
is um i've enjoyed every single
conversation
i'm often frustrated at that this hasn't
attracted more people and i know that's
on me i love curious like people just
show up and don't know what the topic is
yeah that's on me
like just shut up whatever it is who
cares right who cares who the topic is
just show up and have a conversation
everyone eats
everyone knows something about prison
you don't need to be an expert on it
but having that space that you don't
need to be an expert and seeing what the
group
generates and my hypothesis is yet to
figure
like i would love lots of people to be
doing this and having dozens of solution
raisings on a specific topic so we can
vote
we can see what comes out of parallel
ones and vote on the best solution and
then make it
um was my vision to begin with and i
don't know if that is ever going to
happen
because i think solution raising
is the thing that the world doesn't know
it needs so they're not even looking for
it they're not here and they're like a
conversation that can save you but no
in an hour and i'm like yeah watch one
and that's the other part
is that they're not designed to be
watched
they're designed to be participated in
um if you're gonna watch it watch the
last half right
where we're actually coming up with
solutions but even then there's a very
different
energy and quality to being in the group
talking about it
versus watching someone else doing that
like we're not doing this to entertain
we're doing this
for our benefit as well as whatever the
ideas come out
and i think a lot of people get
frustrated um
when they do come to a one-off one
especially and there's a powerful
solution we come up with it's like right
where do we make it it's like we're not
that's not we don't have 10 000 people
every single um issue like right there
was
an amazing app that's exactly what a lot
of us have been thinking about with
environmentalism and recipes and how to
vote with your dollar
to a certain degree and someone in the
game b space has made it it's up it's
ready
and mark campbell commented on it saying
like yeah but why aren't these things
like it's been out for a year why didn't
we know about it why didn't it's like
yes exactly the same beautiful beautiful
solution keeps happening
and we don't do anything with it because
there aren't 10 000 people to make it
usable
right and so i'm trying to fix a problem
that other people don't even know exists
and that's my frustration but i think
when they come and see that we can
create that powerful step
forward that like i keep saying and all
this stuff with solution raising like if
we can
if we can drastically improve anything
we can drastically improve
everything and do it in a voluntary way
where if our food solution doesn't work
for you you could create your own with
ten thousand people
if your it doesn't work for you but you
want a a beautiful solution for just you
yeah no that's not gonna work but spend
your money on it but a way for us to
come together and co-create solutions
and so that's my a bit of my current one
so far
and also that i really appreciate the
people who show up regularly
gary and eric and the people who come
with one off and try it i appreciate
everyone who shows up to them
and figuring out my vision is anyone
comes to this so we can break off into
groups and you can do it with strangers
but i think there is a different
deeper quality to doing it with people
you you know
right that you know that would help a
lot and i know this is not your fault
hey jubilee i
i get that but what would help a lot
would be that everyone that attended one
of these things that you
got their email address created a little
database sent out an email every week
saying this week's solution raising is
on blah blah blah here's the link
and listen that's not to say everyone's
going to turn up every week but but it
just creates a little bit of
you know momentum in the mind of of the
people listen i
i hate that kind of too so i'm not
being critical i'm just saying it really
would be helpful
if you or if you could find someone to
do that for you probably would be a
more more realistic solution do you have
a um
a solution raisins gmail address account
no because i because i start so many
fires i never know when to start like
you know it's like crowdfunding right
because i was i was gonna like because
i've been thinking as i said i've been
watching about
sponsorship and stuff like that and
things to do and
not what to do and that and it's all
about audience right
so therefore i was gonna ask you
same as what eric has just said so like
right
let's do a survey of the people who've
actually shown up
right you have participated and find out
more about them right because then i
think a discovery session
on who they are what they look to
what their audience is right so you can
build up so that you've got
looking for what sort like all audience
and what they're doing
and also i was gonna this kind of ties
into your your stuff that you're doing
tomorrow which i thought about
as well you know i mean and as i said do
discover these sessions with you know
like you said
the first ten do discovery sessions and
find out
and also what you could maybe offer
would be a a kind of
personal solution reason for
their business project exactly what
we're doing this is exactly what the mlm
is except not your project because your
project is together tech bring your
project together tech we'll figure that
out
this is your you who you're your project
right yeah what is it that's not
solution
but yeah like personal raising like in
order to find
maybe prospects who would
kind of sponsor stuff we need to find
people the audience and what they're
interested in
and then find out maybe find prospects
somewhere down the line
and they say well what audiences have
you got and then kind of match the two
up
and then say right this person's
audience is that
you know prospect says oh i'm looking to
sponsor something for
this is what how do i you know what i
mean and they might have the same
kind of target audience in mind and
helping to
just you know what i mean so this is why
kind of like a a survey
of participants who've been here i don't
know i don't want to do it either
because it's very gay being shy
you know but i think we're going to have
to do that if you want to get it
absolutely do i just can't do that it's
not even i don't want to
it's because i can't do what i don't
want to like my brain
even even this powerpoint presentation
that i'm like i'm super passionate about
this mlm
i and eric saw it yesterday it's very
it's very rough i will go through now
and and
and edit it i needed to have a deadline
and if i had to do that every week i
wouldn't be doing this because it's
costing me
everything else to be able to do that
and that is it's like putting out an
email list doing those things i need
someone who can do the executive side
which is why for the mlm i'm like those
are i need i instead of putting it up to
my network
i put it out to game b to say i want i
need the marketing and executive
functioning people
that is who we need from day one so we
can do that kind of stuff
did you did you get any response yeah
we'll have we'll see who's there
tomorrow and if it's not the right
people that's fine i'm gonna keep going
until i find the right people we'll
figure out how to make it pretty and
make it
make it um usable and then we'll go
forward but this is about
solutions in itself i would love to hear
from both of you because i have my
vision of what i would like solution
raising to look like but i don't want it
to taint
what you guys are going to offer what
would you love solution raising to look
like
in the world in the ideal future
beyond the parameters a hundred thousand
dollars and ten thousand well well i
don't think because you've been trying
to get all the people to hold solution
raisins and that's not
kind of worked because i think i think
people like
it come because of you right they like
the way you do it
and they don't feel confident to do it
themselves so i suppose
training to do help them do that but
you need to know the order what they're
interested in as well and that's why i
was thinking about more along the
personal
kind of business and then because
there's enough dead good brains
in game b you know good really thinkers
you know if people come with as i said
you know i
said kind of offering the solution
raisins as a
and someone could maybe sponsor the
solution raising for this specific thing
i think that would be a good idea but
again you need to find out
the audiences of the people who'd be
maybe wanting that
and maybe someone who's interested in
sponsoring that
you know i mean would they be the same
people you know i mean
so what i want to hear and you're
allowed to share anything
you want to share but like what say we
got all that
right what is what does solution raising
look like with that right like what does
the future look like in the ideal
scenario where whatever the path is got
already we already got there what is it
what does it look like in the
library i i kind of see the solution
raising in its current
form as being you know like the really
beginning
what it is it's a really loud shouty
version
of figuring out solutions for things
right it's it's it's
uh because as you already said it's not
really
like the ongoing creation of solutions
to problems in a spontaneous organic
kind of way this is not how we do things
at the moment right so
i see this as um hopefully
right the beginning of solution
creative problem solving being built
into the very fabric of everything that
we do right
and so that you know over time feedback
mechanisms will emerge
such that you know someone's having a
problem with fungal infection on their
cabbages right and that
that need goes out into
the network into the commons whatever it
is right and someone somewhere who has
already figured out this problem or
is interested in figuring out this
problem puts themselves in their network
people to work on figuring out that
problem and when they figured it out the
solution goes into the same
you know common so that everyone now has
access to it with a particular tag to
the person who flagged up the thing in
the first place so they get
you know so they get it immediately that
sort of thing and so you know there's
not
you know there's i see it as a sort of
dynamic flow between these
two things and and the thing is that the
transmission of that need is in itself a
gift right i see all of these things as
gifts to the commons and the
transmission of that need is also a gift
because
you are gifting somebody the opportunity
to be of service in meeting that need
right and so it's a
i i i really like this idea of
everything flowing in
and out of this undefinable amorphous
commons space
right and and there's communication
somehow
that like a supply and demand thing is a
little bit like the notion of the
invisible hand of the market right where
supply and demand
find perfect equilibrium it's exactly
the same thing where
needs and problems and solutions to
those needs and problems
find balance and and and harmony in that
space
that's my ideal vision of the future do
you want to share
more of yours carrie or i'm perfectly i
just want to well
if we were already there
we'd be all be doing stuff eh so but but
as i said
i do think i do think making it a bit
more personal
about people who who come and
i'm finding out more about them you know
what i mean i think i think that's
that's the key and finding out what
they're interested in
because i don't think they're going to
run with the ball and hold them
themselves
but if there's i think if there's an
opportunity say right okay
um just found out what you're doing
right
have you got any problems with this do
you want to do a solution
reasons on this and you get people who
maybe you're collaborating with you're
working with
to maybe come on board and then do that
and then say like say like do it do a
set of
maybe four sessions with them
just about them i'm finding out more
about them and then as i said they can
take part in the
the this is literally carrie what two
days will we talk about the mlm this is
it's a six week course getting together
with the same people whether i'm there
or not
and we talk about what does your health
look like what do your relationships
look like yeah
your resources look like and then we do
a solution raising on a big thing
and so it's like yeah finding out more
about your actual but jubilee this this
all kind of
it all mushes up together for me you
know what i mean like
it just all kind of mushes up together
and it's kind of no separating it really
um because this is the type of thing you
know i mean so it's
kind of all mushed up so it's different
difficult for me to separate
things totally fine you're absolutely
right kerry and in the conversation
about you know what's your health like
that is going to spill over into all
kinds of other things because as you say
it does all mush up together so
you know the health conversation is not
going to be entirely around health just
in the same way that your aspirations
are not going to be entirely
you know there's going to be a huge
amount of of overlap between them but
the point is
that overall in the course of these four
sessions you get to know each other
pretty well you know
well yeah because i think that's that's
the i think this is
right what i find most important about
these right
is that you do actually get to know
people yeah well
you know what i mean and and i like that
because there's no other place that you
can actually go and turn up
and get to know others you know what i
mean like as i said there's people
dropping there's people dropping all the
time
and over time you get to know them and
you get to find out more about them
in the conversations as well so i think
that's the
that that's the most important thing i
think for me
is to getting to know people on a on a
honest on an honest way
because like you know i mean because
like whenever you try and sort like
go and join something online they're
always trying to sell you some shite or
other
and you're just like nah
i mean yeah okay so i'm going to share
my version of the ideal solution raising
in the future
it's going to come out and then we can
switch over to the what we would love to
do
or what we could do right now if we had
10 000 people 100 000
um so my vision is still somewhat the
same that many people
are any time you have a problem whether
it is there's mold on your cabbages
or fungus on your cabbages or whether
it's i don't know how to garden at all
you know where to go to get those
solutions and sometimes it is as easy as
somebody just giving you that little
piece of information
but other times it's going to be right
everyone wants to know how to grow food
how do we get a system of information
that makes it
easier for everyone and then stop
telling people it's easy enough you
should be able to do it
what isn't easy for you and keep
improving it and improving it
um is the idea that it can you can we
start with a powerful step forward but
then we continually improve it to meet
more and more of the fringes of society
people who want to garden but just can't
right what is that can't how do we get
you to
get you through it without telling you
you just need to do it right you just
need to push through it by yourself
having a true crowd-sourced way to solve
problems of change
there would also be a process to
actually work through
to either vote in the best ideas so now
we're going to fund the best food app
um and then are you in or and or
here are the ideas which one do you want
to put money towards which one do you
vote is the one you would use
and then we create it and maybe that i i
can envision a process that has the
crowd involved in most of it
but just like with solution raising
where i thought that like
the world wants this they want to come
and solve problems maybe they don't
maybe one in a thousand people want to
come solve problems
but the one in a thousand can solve it
for the rest and they do
want the solutions that come out of it
and so to be able to honor that and be
able to do something like personal raise
personal solution raising for your own
life in a peer group
or it's like how can you move your step
yourself forward with what we have now
and then from that generating ideas and
knowing there's a
there's both people who are committed to
making the idea because we have
the tools to do that we have the system
to do that and
therefore you can get as involved as you
want right that any of these ideas we
have generated
they if we thought they were powerful
they could just move forward
right and just put out into the world
and there was enough people to say yes i
like it i would use it and then
great what features and benefits do we
want it to have and then let's pay for
it to get coded
and then we use it and improve it
because we own it we can improve it
so that is my um
vision i don't know how far in the
future it is because i do think the mlm
is possibly going to get us there
or take a completely different direction
as all of my fires seem to take trains
you can't control fires they just like
have a mind of their own they just go on
their own path
so now i would love to hear what
we could generate i'm gonna try not to
break all of my previous ideas into it
but i'm sure they'll be here
um with ten thousand people and a
hundred thousand dollars
in solution raising what would that
infrastructure look like to be able to
actually create these ideas
or bring more people so we get better
ideas and more people to know about it
i think if you're at them people you
could establish local hubs
by and the local hub might just be one
person
to start off with right because you're
talking about the the fringes of society
after people that you know probably
don't know anyone on the fringe of
society
you know what i mean they don't get like
as i said i've been um
every tuesday and thursday we've been
volunteering we've been giving out free
food that's
you know destined for the bin just being
given from the supermarkets and
just actually talking to people on the
streets while they're trying to give
them free food and often don't want free
food
you know what i mean and getting them
and just the actual
like because of what's going on in the
world right because of the actual
they're too scared to talk to anyone
they're too scared to go need anyone
and the amount of kind of the ones you
do stop and tell you
how lonely and isolated the feeling
and how how to work the feeling and and
stuff like that
and it's just awfully good because i had
one woman came to me the other day
and she told me she was like caring for
a
dad who's got dementia caring for a
mother who was honorable to her
and a son who's got mental health issues
right
and i asked her did she have any friends
she said no
she's got no friends and i said
what she said well whatever they've
tried to to
have friends they've always been
honorable to me and that
and the fear that she had of actually
talking to somebody
like joe given a bunch of flowers that
would give give it away
and uh she cliented eyes out and it's
just that
loneliness and that isolation like
nobody's actually reaching out to people
on a face-to-face level anymore and i
can and okay everything's great online
but you've got to have the face-to-face
local as well um so i think little
people who are online who'd be willing
to be hubs to go up into the local
communities and find out
people like because i asked one lady who
i made something for i said how's your
social life
what would those people be doing when
they go out though because are they
having solution raising
like what are they actually actually
talking to people
you know what i mean talking to people
and finding out what
problems that are out there that what
their needs are and
finding that audience again it's about
an audience you know
so i think there's also so when you said
that you know the fringes of society i
want to be clear i think every single
human being is on the fringes of society
you might fit into game a 90 there's
still 10 percent you do not fit into
game a there's still 10
you freaking suck but you have to
pretend you don't
and this is about solving problems
together not going out and creating
charity for people
um of which i am both the receiver and
giver of on
on and off to basis and there's nothing
wrong with that model but this is about
i don't want to go out to my local
community and convince people they
should be doing solution raisings
because a lot of those people that are
on the fringes in that way
are very used to charity model and so
that's what they want it's like
you know if you put out free food on the
internet people are like yeah and i need
it delivered and it's not gluten-free
what do you like it's like
there's nothing wrong with that because
you should have food that beats your
diet but i would rather be able to
invite them to like come
solve your food security needs right
come actually be part of that
without needing to convince them of it
if that makes sense like this is
and if we just start solidarity if we
just start right we're all in this
together what how could we move this
forward
that's an interesting word because most
people don't know what it means
they see it on paper they kind of
understand it but actual
solidarity doesn't happen like that
so i don't know how you teach solidarity
to people who haven't got a clue what
that actually means
you know what i mean you'd let them come
and do it right because there's a very
big difference between
and it happens on the other side as well
right people who
are affluent or people who feel like
they have their together
are like oh yeah like my sister who's
like great i'm going to start
communities but i want to live in them
i'm like
no that's charity not solidarity you
need to figure out don't create a
society you wouldn't want to live in
create a community you'd want to be part
of
and that's that's part of it is
that solidarity piece is you have
solutions to your own problems and
together we can do it
so what would you want right not a bunch
of people with affluence being like how
could we get together and solve poverty
for those poor impoverished people
i want the people in poverty to be like
that's what annoys me the most you know
i mean you've got
you've got people who are sort of like
well up there made loads of money and
deciding that they want us
you know help you know and i often hear
them talking about
you know the po are we going to fix this
for the poor but you don't know
anybody who's poor now off
you know i mean so so how'd you sell
them to solidarity to stop being like
you know that's
so that's we don't need to sell it like
how do we
get people like solution racing doesn't
need seven point
we don't need to appeal to 7.5 billion
people we need 10 000 people so how
could we get
to 10 000 people or what if we had 10
000 people because i do think our mlm
structure will get us to 10 000.
what do we do with them right what does
that we have a hundred thousand dollars
to make a website
for solution raising itself so that
people can come and be part of it
and the solutions can actually get made
right that their money isn't just going
towards that website
but towards actually creating the
solutions what could that
look like right what could we do in that
realm for
10 000 people in a hundred thousand
dollars for that ten thousand people
right not going out and like all those
poor starving kids in africa no
like the poor starving kids in africa
will figure it out they will figure it
out if we figure out how to feed
ourselves
and we offer that to them and we have a
pool of stuff
they're gonna actually want what they
solve as opposed to the white people who
come in and build the beautiful garden
that the hippos then come in and eat
they wonder why none of the locals help
them build it
yeah we knew the hippos were gonna come
eat your tomatoes that's what they do
every year
yeah um i don't know
um i don't know what you're gonna do
with them said i think you need to know
who they are
and what they're interested in so again
it's back to knowing your audience and
knowing what
that's i don't said this that's a good
place to start what could that look like
without because i'm never sitting down
with all of those people right
oh no i'm not sitting down with all of
those people like i
would you know like for them to sit down
with each other and get that information
from them
right how does it look like for them to
that's part of what the six week course
is
is here's where i am here's where i want
to be here's what's stopping me
those six people at least know who you
are what's stopping you and helping you
move forward
i don't know if the greater group needs
to know it but there are ways to collect
that data and make it available to you
and to the people who can directly help
you that could be done with a hundred
thousand dollars
without needing to be you know
the um like the connoisseur of your life
right like that is
that's more charity than solidarity in
my mind like coming and saying
i'm going to solve your problems for you
versus we're going to give you the tools
to solve your problems yourself
what does it look like to solve your
problem yourself
right so maybe that what would help you
solve your problems right what would
help you come and be part of a
small group of people to crowdsource
your problems whether personal or global
right the ones you care about
[Music]
that's not addict over to you
yeah i mean the the
the solution raisings have come up with
quite a few things right and so what
we do with ten thousand people a hundred
thousand dollars is is any of the things
that the solution raises would come up
with right i mean any of those
any of those put into action and seem to
be working reinforces the value of the
process of solution raising right
because it has brought about this thing
which
you know is now in place and is working
and he's doing the thing that it was
supposed to do and whatever so
yeah i mean to a certain extent it
really doesn't matter where you start
you just need to start somewhere and
start building you know what i mean i
mean you always you always start from a
position of zero
going from zero to something is is in
many ways the hardest step
going from something to more is usually
a lot easier
okay so right so the people who've
participated in solution ratings so far
would would you help us to like through
chat getting a kind of survey put
together
and then asking them to fill it in just
the ones who participated
and then we can see you know what's what
and then we can maybe ask the people who
have actually watched it
but not participated in and then see
what they say because i'm about to come
back to facebook
which can screaming because i said i've
been offered for a while
uh and as i said i've took a deep dive
into sales and marketing and sponsorship
and all of that
so i feel as if i've got more of a clue
on stuff
so now i need to go and i'll you know
target audiences and stuff like that
and building surveys so i need to go and
have a look at that
and use solution racing as your pet
project that would be awesome to be
like bring people in and be part of part
of solution raising but this part
is like we have 10 000 people right we
have 10 000 people who tried solution
raising love solution raising want to
have a solution raising
what do we do with what what could we do
with 10 000 people who want solution
raising
with a hundred thousand dollars right
they're like yes here's ten dollars
um not that i think that what eric
suggested is possibly a solution we just
pick
one of the things right and make it and
so
even though these aren't parallel
solution raisins with various people
having them
potentially out of the two dozen plus
we've done
having a little blurb of here's what we
came up with for food here's what we
came up with for for this and that
um which one would you want to see in
the world right now
because i think that people want to vote
for prison and slavery in those ones
but those aren't the ones that you're
necessarily going to use
which one would help you most in your
life right now and making that for
people and showcasing that part of what
i would love to see from whatever
absolution raising becomes
is like a way
to play together with our data in a way
where it's like okay someone
someone loves this idea that came out of
a solution raising and they're taking
this on as a project
whether it's successful or a failure
that information is going back into the
system so they're playing with things
like different structures of governance
different structures of decision making
different
methods of conversation uh for
how do you have a conversation with 10
000 people how do you have 10 000 people
put input into an idea
so that it's going to meet most of their
needs right and i think that
there are tools that almost do that
online you can put up the surveys and
put out those things but what could we
that we could make one from scratch for
solution raising if we had 100 000
would be that right like the idea isn't
that
an amalgamator of the ideas that come
out of solution raising
a voting to be able to say which one is
the best for each option
um to say which the best overall right
what is because if they're all powerful
solutions for food for clothing for
shelter
which is my priority and then making
that one and
success or failure learning from it and
growing and seeing
right if there's various projects a new
one starts each month do you want to be
on this one do you want to wait till the
next one
to be able to be as involved as you want
to be whether it's just
just coming to the solution raising and
having a conversation
just putting your funding in or being
instrumental in being on the board of
directors for that project
and and following it forward right or
being one of the more fringe
giving advice and voting so the board of
directors can act on it that there's
different ways to play and being able
instead of having one structure then
it's
more diverse right you can say okay
we're going to try with the board of
directors we're going to try it without
a board of directors we're going to try
it
um completely crowdsourced right how do
you crowdsource an app like how do you
decide on the layout and this and we're
going to break into groups and do
a contest and the winner gets 10
000 and that other 90 000 goes to
creating the project i mean there's
any idea can be put into the system and
come out with something
or be a failure right if you're like i
want to create this app and nobody likes
it
it's it goes it doesn't happen i know
that was a lot that was
a lot of different ideas but so you
think
i if say like someone comes here with an
idea that they want to do
and nobody wants it do you think that
they might get a bit off
then nobody's taking any notice
they might get a bit off or they
might realize that maybe maybe their
idea isn't as good as they thought it
was you know what i mean no one's taking
any choices i mean
yeah it could be either right
and how tight are you to your idea right
because that's part of it is people are
like
i know me it's like all these other
worlds that changing i'm like oh but
it's not quite right
right i'm not going to jump onto yours
because it's not transparent enough it's
not crowd-sourced enough it's not
i don't feel like i can contribute and
so realizing that being like if you need
to reinvent the wheel every time there's
one feature that doesn't work for you
yeah no wonder right you have we create
a food app and someone's like
you don't have my grandmother's recipe
so i'm going to create a whole new one
instead of adding the removes recipe
is like right if you're constantly doing
that that's going to need to showcase
if there's a big enough thing that this
one doesn't do you'll be able to get a
group of people on board i think that
just tells you is your idea of
viable before you put into hundreds of
hours and tens of thousands of dollars
right
are people gonna want it and that's what
we're doing is we're solving the supply
demand before
taking audience come back to audience
isn't it and finding out what people
what and what they're needing on a
personal level
and then come back it's a much better
way of doing i mean at the moment if
you've got an idea for
a business then you go to investors
right and if you can't get investors
then
you know it's the same thing right you
sort of think oh maybe my idea isn't as
good or as marketable or as appealing as
ever as i thought it was right and
but the thing is investors are a very
very tiny handful of people who've got
lots of money whereas this is a much
much larger
crowd of peers right i mean ideally
these are peers these are not people
you're competing with these are people
who are
in your community and what we're trying
to do is is is you know get the biggest
bang for our buck as it were you know
allocate resources to the place where
they're going to be
do the most good for the most people
kind of thing so yeah i mean i i did
you know it's out of the hands of one or
two people who actually control the
purse strings and it's in the hands of
the entire community decide what is and
is not viable
now if it starts to become the fact that
someone comes along with a really good
idea and for whatever sort of political
reasons within the group
that idea is not looked at now that's a
real problem and that means that
that needs to be addressed
um so yeah i mean i you know that may or
may not that kind of thing may or may
not emerge within the ten thousand
camps within the ten thousand where
people gather like-minded souls around
themselves and then you know there's
automatic
um antipathy towards other factions with
it i mean i i don't know that kind of
dynamic may emerge
and that's something that's going to
need to be there i mean hopefully with
the cross pollination of people between
groups that that goes away to a certain
extent because you know people get to
know everyone if not indirectly then
through one or two degrees of separation
everybody knows everyone and so
hopefully but anyway
but yeah it's a very it's it's it's a
definite possibility it's a definite
possibility
i do like because part of my pushback to
having
local groups do solution raising is then
it
somewhat restricts people having local
solutions and a lot of the ideas we come
up with are global solutions right
sometimes the 10 000 people are local to
vancouver right if you're starting a
food co-op it's probably going to be
local but
um coming up with it with a system for a
food co-op
could be global and that would be even
more powerful but doing the personal
raising
locally helps more because then you're
like you know what i mean like i can't
help find carry a job because i don't
know when where you live
right like that's not where i got it i
can't even help me find a job you know i
mean
yeah which like if we lived in the same
place that would be and you were in a
group of six would be easier because i
guarantee you someone in that group of
six locally
know somebody who's looking for work
like someone who's looking for workers
and so they you know i'll talk to my
friend brian right he
he needs cleaners if you're willing to
do cleaning yeah absolutely we could
have you a job tomorrow
that's how most people find a job right
is through those connections because
there's 300 people looking for a job
and so having local like when you're
doing it your own life i think
local is actually the best way to go um
and with time zones and stuff that that
makes general sense
it's it's based on your time zone but
also based on um
like if for some reason my only time i'm
available is 2 am my time then maybe i'm
talking to people
right like maybe that's because there's
no one vancouver wants to talk at 2am
but at least i know i'm in with that
group of people right so and maybe there
are a group of locals who want to talk
at 2am i don't know
[Music]
yeah well that's a sad experience it's
been awesome and even people who are now
don't know anyone because everyone's
kind of starting to be in the same boat
which is
you know like because i've always had
jobs no i've always kind of
maybe left the job because i didn't like
it but i've always managed to be able to
get something
you know i mean even if it wasn't all
singing and dancing it was just
something
um but this time round it it's just
shocking
you know what i mean and as i said it's
not just me um it's loads of people
everyone know and i said after you get
past a certain age
it's like nobody wants to know you know
what i mean and i find that really sad
because you've got
you built up loads of experience know
how to deal with people
and that and they're like no because you
you're not obviously funky enough
looking
you know or you're too scary looking oh
you don't have this yeah
something that's coming through what
you're talking is i'm sorry for
interrupting is um
like not even so much local solution
racing or
but like life area focused solution
raising
right where like for you to have access
to other people who are looking for work
now you guys are each other's
competition especially if you're local
but at the same time my guess is is
there is a powerful solution that 10 000
people looking for work
could come up with to create their own
ubi even right that there's like
10 000 people going through a divorce 10
000 people dealing with co-parenting 10
000 people
where you're not necessarily starting at
10 000 but you're getting together with
five people who are going through that
same thing and
having a solution raising right it's pro
it's personal
i need a job this is what i'm going
through my life and here's where i can't
find it and i'm
i'm in the same boat as everyone else
i've kind of been doing
doing this like as i said there's
there's a woman called monty
runs the police box and you know they
have pop-up things and that
so we're having a chat with her about
stuff and she's like oh i never thought
about that so
the women who have met like joe's a chef
and
um you know joe's a therapist rasheen's
a chef
monty's you know got all this stuff and
the other going on
so we have started helping each other
like and as i said when i'm speaking
with leanne
and she just said you know nobody's
gonna give us a job
so and she was kind of like you know at
the stage where she was wanting to set
up her own business not
so i think i think loads of people now
are actually going to be forced into
business even if they don't want to do
it
right what i've seen in the mlm
community is how many people
can't get a job regularly so they think
that the mlm and i'm like it's not it's
just
you might as well play the lottery
that's how ridiculous mlms are
but i think that there is i was just
coming up
like working to like this is with okay
so
i can't work for somebody else it's i'm
disabled and i can't so
society's version of a solution is like
great than work for yourself and it's
like
no no no working for somebody else is
easier
working for yourself and taking on all
of that risk and not knowing if there's
a regular paycheck
is way more stressful and i can't handle
that as much and that's what our entire
society is set up as those are your two
options
work for yourself or work for someone
else and there has to be a third option
which is like worker cooperatives right
what could we do together
getting five or six people together what
are our skill sets together and how
could we
facilitate each other because one person
will be good at marketing and one person
will be getting yeah
i think i think it's i think it's the
marketing thing that's going to be
stumping most people
right so because like as i said
marketing agencies and all these people
who do marketing charge your fortune
right and there's loads of stuff out
there and that so even
i'm the evil yeah and um you can't
no so i think right so say like i'm
helping
leanne and who's setting up a business
and
i'm like the pair of us you know
interested in doing
we don't come from the evil world right
so so trying to get a gang together who
might help us
with that business because we're having
to do it because no one will give us a
job
so i think if i could find people who'd
be willing to sort of like sit with me
right this is
this is me business what i'm gonna have
to do would you please help me kind of
market it or give us ideas on marketing
strategies
content strategy so there's all sorts of
different strategies i could do with
that with hands on so if i could get
people to actually
go through a solution reasons with the
different strategies
and maybe give me some like things i can
take away and do
you know what i mean put in place and
try and see how they work and if that
doesn't work that would be really good
so i think that is something we could do
with ten thousand people and a hundred
thousand dollars
is get that type of information
of what are you struggling with right
now and how do we form groups around
that
that are both the personal groups like
yes i need a job now i need to pay rent
i need to pay like how do we
how do we solve that for people but also
the bigger piece of the labor
the how do we create worker cooperatives
how do we create a thing where i don't
have to put in all the marketing
to find someone so i can clean their
house they just know i'm a good cleaner
and someone else vouches for me and i
just
have a roster of people to clean houses
for without anything to put in all that
work
their solutions can definitely do and so
something is finding that's hard it's
hard to find the people to have a
conversation with who are in the same
boat
and creating the system that makes that
easier so you're like oh my god
teachers right now right they're under
so much stress
i do not envy them under this pandemic
but like getting a bunch of them
together and saying right what could we
do
even though we're in a union even though
we're like like what could happen
even if it's just solidarity or even if
it's just a conversation to vent right
um being able to have access to that
right
all the other people in britain who are
who are over 50 and can't find a job
because no one can see their value
despite the fact they're probably more
valuable than the 25 30 year olds yeah
which is also the ridiculousness of our
current gaming world all of these people
and youtube
like mark zuckerberg drop out of
universities start these tech companies
but then they need you to have a phd to
work for them
or people who you know can't find child
care so they create their own company
and then they need
need people to work on we like single
moms to work on weekends it's like
they design a company around their needs
but they're not actually meeting the
same need for their
for their employees whereas together we
can meet our own needs and that is what
what solution raising is about whether
it's personal or global
we can together meet our own needs and
so a structure that just helps you find
those people to have a conversation with
whether it's
solution raising the topic of the day or
whether it's solution or using for your
own life able to facilitate that i think
would be powerful
especially we already have the 10 000
people looking for that instead of
right
anything else coming up for you eric
yes but completely unrelated to this
it's actually
completely related to a whole different
thing that i'm involved in but actually
it's been
it's been a bit of a moment of insight
for me
um i'm not exactly sure what triggered
it um it was while you were talking
jubilee and i can't think of anything in
particular that he said that would have
triggered it but but something
while you were talking triggered this
cascade of of thoughts about continuity
is some other
i mean a thing called the prism and
continuity is is a topic we've been
sort of circling around and as
i was listening to you i was i had this
realization about multiple continuities
existing simultaneously right and so
as i'm listening to you i sort of
drifted off
from listening to you and lost track of
what you were saying because i was
looking at your face and looking at your
mouth and then this led me to think well
hang on here's two continuities right
here there's the continuity of what
she's saying
there's the continuity of movement in
her
face and body there's the continuity of
the bookshelf behind her like a static
continuity right and
and all of these things somehow exist
all of these
somewhat independent narrative
lines narrative arcs exist in in the
same
sort of space right there's this
n-dimensional meta space in which all of
these continuities exist simultaneously
and there is no
continuity per se right there's just
threads
intersecting around in this in this meta
space so yeah
some something like that something like
that so as i say not really directly
related to what we were talking about
but cool nevertheless everything is
always related
what did that bring up for me that was
um
how along the lines of the ceo making a
job for themselves and not for everyone
else
i don't remember what it what it was
except being able to come together and
create solutions together where you
don't
you can see the oh it was it was that
that there's a lot of people in the game
it happens all the time i know i do it
too where it's like right what we need
is everyone on the same page
right everyone on the blah everyone here
and it's like that never
is never gonna be step one getting 10
000 people to agree this is the next
step that's very different than needing
all 10 000 people to agree right picking
a random 10 000 people and finding them
pick something to agree on versus
creating a food out being like what 10
000 people want to create this
and doing it in a way
that it's for you but you don't get to
control anybody else right nobody else
gets to lead the one and only way
there's both right i mean there's room
for both of these things because you
know if you've identified a problem and
you want to gather 10 000 people around
that problem then then great right that
fantastic but having 10 000 people as a
sort of
think tank right what are identifying
problems right looking for things that
are maybe
underneath the surface a little bit that
aren't so obvious but they actually
drive a whole bunch of other problems
and figuring out ways to
maybe tackle those you know that that's
all that's also a value a more
exploratory kind of kind of
um group not necessarily of ten thousand
right that sounds like a lot to be sort
of on random exploration but
whatever you know and they overlap
between these things as well
just because you're working on a food
cooperative doesn't mean you can't also
be involved in some other ones right
it's also why we're not stopping at ten
thousand people right it's more yeah
yeah right
absolutely if you needed a group of
people to
you know brainstorm solutions for a job
brainstorm solutions for
your kid can't sleep at night right now
or whatever it happens to be
out of that 10 000 people i guarantee
you there are five who can
meet on your schedule speak your
language and are dealing with that same
problem
and dealing with it aren't or have dealt
with that problem right well my kid was
young here's what we did
take it or leave it right not the one
solution
works for everyone because there is no
solution that works for everyone but
just having access to those ten thousand
people i think is huge
if there are ten thousand people who
want to help one another create
solutions which i think most of us do so
we have the same
problems we all eat we all care about
even if we can't we don't have enough
capacity to care about the big
world issues we still care about them i
don't think
nearly i don't think there's maybe one
percent of the population or less
that would choose to buy a watch at the
same price point that was made with
slave labor or not slave labor right
even if we're all talking on
labor devices it's like people want to
do good it's just overwhelming people
have the same issues it's just like
which one's my biggest issue right maybe
maybe my biggest issue isn't health it's
relationships
and so everyone else concentrating on
health is going to annoy me
but like right but we'll get to
relationships next week it's like
if there's no additional cost and no
additional inconvenience and a choice
between using something that
that involves slave labor or not then
then i agree there's that
but i think for a lot of people it
wouldn't take a huge differential in
cost or a huge differential
inconvenience because
the thing is we're so detached from what
it actually is like we you know we may
know
in our heads that children are digging
you know
cobalt out of the ground with no
protective gear for top and tapani a day
we
we may know but but we don't actually
see it right it's not in front of us
it's not our children and so we can
i mean we do it all the time i heard
rupert sheldon talking about this he's a
biologist and he's you know he's saying
ever since i was a kid i've you know
i've had lots of pets and you know used
to grow plants and blah blah blah and
i've always felt deeply connected with
plants and animals and then when i went
to school into university
in order to study plants and animals the
first thing you do is kill them and chop
them up into little pieces and you know
this is
and in order to do that you have to
distance yourself
from the thing that you're studying you
know second and and he never felt that
that was right especially when you're
studying the living world right
to kill it before you study it seems
like a little bit of a
missing the point sort of thing you know
um so yeah it feels a bit like that
studying living systems funny i was
thinking because i have a biology degree
and when you go to a biology you
basically have to do the dissect the cat
dissect the this dissect that course its
anatomy
and i i was like i don't need i don't
need that i really don't i'm not and so
i filled it with economics i felt with
everything else because i was able to
and i didn't need to necessarily
distance myself like you're learning
anything new by doing it right you can
see all pictures you can see photographs
and 3d
blah blah blah of all of this you don't
actually need to do
there's nothing to learn really by doing
it it's just
the it's the act of doing it right i
mean i guess you could argue if you
wanted to be a surgeon then there is
some efficacy in
learning at an earlier age perhaps the
skill with a scalpel and blah blah blah
but perhaps you could make that argument
but otherwise i just
i don't see it and yeah i mean if
if you are forced to detach yourself in
order to do that
then you are now in
how can i put this you're in a white
coat
um lab rat relationship always with the
thing that you'll study you know there's
no respect there's no or
there's no um appreciation there's no
you know wonder you know what i mean
it's just it's just this thing that you
poke and prod
and cut up and put under microscopes and
it's just
yeah and science is rife with that in a
way of like
okay we need to take we need it to be
pure science we need to take the rat and
put it in a pure cage with nothing else
and it's like
that's not pure though that's not who
they are that's not
they're not you know they're not part of
their ecosystem they're not part of
their rat culture they're not part like
no that's not and so we've been studying
for
decades animals that are under high
stress
low social and it's like oh and then the
drug that works on them but not on us
or vice versa and so it is i think i
think very relevant i know today we
didn't get quite to a solution for
smooth raising
turns out that's the topic we can't
tackle solution
but i'd still like to do what we do at
the end of the other ones which is what
do we think is the most powerful thing
we could do
for solution raising with ten thousand
people and a hundred thousand dollars
i mean like i said before it doesn't
matter pick one and do it right and show
that it works and that
that's the most powerful thing you can
do is show the world that it works
and that recruits more people to the
idea and
and so on i would agree with eric
do something make it work then show them
then they can't go
oh no
until until it actually does something
it's a pie in the sky idea right it
might be a good one but it's a pie in
the sky idea until it actually does
something
and and for a lot of people everything's
pie in the sky until it's actually done
something right i mean that's the
difference between the earlier doctors
and the people and
and the big herd of sheep that follow in
later on once the once the early
adopters have all accepted it and it's
normal to them
so you know that's that's how life is
my my i don't want to disagree with you
guys that that is the most powerful one
for but the issue is
we don't have 10 000 people to put like
if you know what i mean like we need to
have done the
good project to get the 10 000 to say we
have them to create it it's a little bit
of a chicken and egg scenario
yeah you need to do small scale things
with smaller numbers of people and
and that is that is part of it and so
the most powerful thing reason i can see
forward besides having just an app
of yes we can vote on things together we
can you know
a basic something that can facilitate
solution raising we help you find your
group help you
um host if you want to host one uh
creating
the mlm creating the way to
exponentially grow to bring people in to
meet their own needs
instead of doing the global issues yeah
because that was my critique
of this this person's beautiful
beautiful app that mark had critiqued on
in my critique when i saw it i'm like
i've been waiting for someone to make
this app and my honest to god was like
oh it's designed for
environmentalists
which is exactly who i wanted to design
it for but that's problematic because
then it's only going to have
environmentalists on it
and they're you know what i mean like
it's therefore like it's preaching to
the converted
what you need is the thing that's going
to help people where they're at
and in so doing is going to help the
planet in so doing is going to
and so there's there's something that's
happening with that but it's something
like food i mean as you said food needs
to be local and finding 10 000 people in
a local area is hard but
something like food you could do a
pretty
you could make a pretty reasonable dent
in people's food
shortages certainly would say 100 people
100 people collaborating and using their
front gardens and their window boxes and
their roof terraces
to do what they can in the space that
they have right and talking to each
other and advising and deciding who's
going to grow broccoli and who's going
to grow onions
and blah blah blah blah blah figuring
that out just just among 100 or so
people i mean i think that is a viable
that is a viable thing to to crack on
with you know
does there's a place like that near me
it's called the croft carbon college
and basically they took a better park
and started growing things and now they
started reaching out and teaching how to
people
to grow things in small places and stuff
like that as well you know so
stuff like that that already exists i
mean even if you're on a 27th floor
apartment you know you've got
a window you can stick a box in the
window and you can grow some herbs or
something you know what i mean i
you know wherever you are i reckon you
can do something
but that's never been exact but this is
exactly part of the process
right within your 100 people you're
going to have complete novices and
you're going to have people who have
been growing stuff for a while and know
a fair bit and so
you know you're communicating with each
other you know my my parsley keeps dying
i don't know what the i'm doing
wrong what is
you know what i mean and and and you
know you you figure it out as a
community and that's part of the
community building in the relationship
building and you know these are all the
fringe
benefits you know you're it's about food
but actually it's about a whole bunch of
other stuff that
happens as a consequence of your
collaboration around
trying to do better job with food
which i do like that is worth the hour
but the ie potential is
just like from our community one where
we talked about the hundred groups of
100 having
a solution raised raising app that does
focused on our needs right so this
group focuses on food this one focuses
on energy this one focuses
and whichever one you want to put your
time and energy towards it's just
it's part of it's finding those hundred
finding those local hundreds and they're
already there i guarantee you don't need
to start them
there's already a facebook group in
vancouver about gardening guaranteed
and just joining it in an urban area
where it's pretty high population
there's it doesn't take long to go knock
on 100 doors
or say 200 doors right because half the
people won't be interested so
you know to go and knock on 200 doors
and you know have a little leaflet and
talk to them for five minutes i mean how
long does it take a couple of weeks
an hour or two a day you know it's not
outside of the realms of
do-ability it really isn't well i think
knocking on people's doors though like
probably get stabbed around here
maybe not now and also yeah jordan
pandemic all right
thank you both for coming to raise
solutions for solution magazine i really
appreciate it
and i will end the recording here oh
i was going to end the meeting